Leaders all over Winchester who recognize the name
because they've studied his books for decades.
Father, we thank you that today
as you bring the word of God to us
with humility and with authority,
we pray that you would bless both
of the voice of humility and authority
with the faith of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
There's one thing that I did not tell you about now,
which you might be wondering about, my name.
You have guessed by now that I am not Asian.
Just fight what you might think as you see the name.
It's actually a Norwegian background.
My great-grandfather emigrated from Norway,
and as he entered into the United States
back in the late 1800s,
and so many Scandinavians were moving into North America,
his name was a nice, normal Ericsson.
Sadly, a customs official encouraged him to change his name.
He said, you know, somebody Ericsson's moving into the Middle West,
you're just going to get lost in the shuffle.
So, to the lasting regret of his assignments,
he chose the name of the village he was from in Norway,
M-O in Norwegian,
pronounced new,
and written down M-O-O by the customs official,
as he entered into the country.
Some of you will remember the Johnny Cross song,
a boy named Sue.
I was a boy named Moo,
and it was an individual experience growing up
with that last hand, as you can imagine.
Back in the day, I played some basketball,
and opposing teams would wonder,
why are they booing this player?
No, they were mooing me last night.
It's been really good to be with the folks yesterday,
at the seminar,
and to experience worship with you this morning.
Thank you.
That was just a delight for those of you who are leading the music.
Thank you for bringing us in the presence of the Lord in that way.
Your hospitality,
those of you who have been involved in welcoming us
and setting up our visit,
it's been a marvelous job.
Thank you so much for that.
I want to turn to a passage that,
if someone were to put a gun to my head,
I would say,
yeah, this is the central idea of Hebrews.
Hebrews has a lot to say.
It's a 13-chapter book,
rich, detailed,
a lot of different things in there.
But again,
if someone were to ask me,
you know,
boy, look down.
Maybe I don't have time to read all of Hebrews.
Certainly, I'm not going to preach on all of Hebrews this morning.
You can rest content with us.
But where do we sort of get to the heart of Hebrews?
Well, I think I would identify that as Hebrews 10, 19-25.
That's the parentheses we're going to look at this morning.
If you have your Bibles,
obviously open up to Hebrews 10, 19-25.
I'm assuming you're all using the new inspired version.
But if you're not,
you could probably still follow along
in whatever unfortunate version you might have.
Hebrews 10, 19-25.
I will be reading this from the NIV.
But again,
whatever Bible you have,
please follow along.
I'm always interested in people seeing where I'm getting my ideas.
Not from my imagination.
Not from my scholarship.
But from the Word of God.
That's fundamental for all of us.
So here's the text.
Therefore, brothers and sisters,
since we have confidence to enter the most holy place of the blood of Jesus,
by a new and living way,
open for us through the curtain that is His body,
and since we have a great priest over the house of God,
let us draw near to God with a sincere heart
and with the fullest spirit that faith brings,
having our hearts sprinkled to cleanse us from a guilty conscience
and having our bodies washed with cured water.
Let us hold on swervingly to the hope we profess,
for He who promised is faithful.
And let us consider how we may spur one another on toward love and good deeds,
not giving up meeting together,
as some are in the habit of doing,
but encouraging one another,
and all the more as you see the day approaching.
What's going on in this text is really obvious right at the surface.
It doesn't take any great insight
to see what the basic structure of our passage is.
Did you see it as we read the text?
Verse 19,
sense.
Verse 21,
And then,
verse 22,
let us draw near.
Verse 23,
let us hold on swervingly.
Verse 24,
let us consider.
Really obvious, isn't it?
First part,
19 to 21,
sense.
Here are certain truths that you know.
On the basis of those truths,
verses 22 and following,
do these three things.
Let us do this.
So again,
right at the surface of our passage,
I mean,
we can all see
a very simple structure
which matches
the fundamental pattern
of New Testament teaching.
Summarized
in 1 John.
We love God.
What?
Because
He first loved us, right?
God is taking the initiative.
It is His grace
that is basic.
And it is on the basis
of what God has done
and because of His grace
that we are called
to respond.
So what God has done,
verses 19 to 21,
what we now
need to do,
verses 22 and following.
To understand this passage
and to understand
Hebrews well,
we need to exercise
our imaginations
just a little bit.
Are you ready for that?
Use your imaginations
just a little bit?
I want to put yourselves
back into the history
of Israel.
You are part of a people
who has just been rescued
from bondage in Egypt.
Most of us will remember
the story
how God worked miracles
to bring His people,
Israel,
out of Egypt
through the Red Sea
making it dry up.
I'm reminded here,
by the way,
I'm going to insert
a little bit of,
I hope,
humor
as a princess.
You know,
there are some scholars
who will say,
oh, you know,
it's no big deal.
It was really
the sea of weeds.
It wasn't the Red Sea.
It was probably
just a shallow munch
or something of that sort.
You know what I mean?
People who are
kind of skeptical
about Scripture.
I remember the story
of a preacher
making that point
to a congregation
only to have
one of his dear,
older Christians
in the back
pop up and say,
pray to God
who drowned
the entire body
of Egyptians
in three inches of water.
a miracle.
God brings
his people.
We know the story
through the Red Sea.
He brings them
to Sinai,
gives them his law.
He brings them
manna in the wilderness.
He causes Moses,
remember,
to use his cane.
That's why I'm
very much this cane,
so I can do
the same thing,
to tap on the earth
and bring water
to the people
as they needed it
in the desert.
So they're seeing
these marvelous things
God is doing.
They're on their way
to a promised land
out here in the desert
and God gives them
as they're traveling
a reminder
of who he is.
He asks Moses
to come up
in a visionary way
and see a sanctuary,
a tabernacle
up in the heavenly realm.
And he says,
Moses,
I want you to build one
for the Israelites,
but they keep carrying
along with them
as a reminder
of who I am.
And so,
the tent is built.
The tent,
and there are various
detailed specifications
toward the end of Exodus.
I don't want to go
into those details.
Certainly not.
But fundamental
to that tent,
as many of you will know,
is that it has two parts.
It has an outer tent
where the Israelite priests
in general could enter
and the Israelite men
could enter
to kind of
step a little bit
of the presence of God
in that way.
But then behind
a very richly
embroidered curtain
there was found
what's called
the Holy of Holies
or the Most Holy Place
where only the high priest
and only once a year
could ever enter.
This inner chamber
behind the curtain
symbolized
represented
the presence
of God
within Israelite.
And again,
our author
in Hebrews
makes this
very clear
and emphasizes
the point
only one person,
the high priest,
only after
a elaborate ceremony
and only once a year
on the Day of Atonement
could enter
into that
Holy of Holies.
So think of yourself
as an Israelite
marching along,
carrying his tent
with you,
constructing over kings
as you think
for the symbolism
again of God
who is holy
and cannot be
easily accessed.
Sometimes we
neglect to think about
just how holy
God is
and how difficult
it can be
to access
his presence.
That's what God
was trying to teach
the Israelites.
But that's the image
we, our author says,
have constantly
to enter
the most holy place
through the curtain,
verse 20,
through the curtain
that is Christ's life.
Think of the torn curtain.
Opened.
Do not bring us
access to God
just as the torn
body of Jesus
nor provides
us access.
Every one of us,
sinners though
we still are,
because of our
priest Jesus,
verse 21,
and his offering
and sacrifice,
enables each of us
to enter
into the presence
of God.
A confidence,
even boldness,
if you translate
the word,
to enter.
What an amazing
privilege
we enjoy.
And we forget that
because we sort of
rush into the presence
of God sometimes
without thinking,
without realizing
the unbelievable
privilege
God has given us
now as New Covenant
people of God
because of the
sacrifice
of Jesus
and our behalf
to enter
into God's
own presence.
So that's what
the prince is about.
in verses
19 to 21.
The author
is reminding us
of things
he's already
said
in the letter
earlier.
He's bringing
them back
to us now
and transforming
them into
a conclusion.
Here now
is the privilege
that we enjoy.
Here is who
we are
as the New Covenant
people of God.
We are to enjoy
that privilege
but we are also
to act
on that privilege.
Privilege
brings responsibility.
We're all familiar
with that
way of looking
at things.
I can remember
in my time
as a scholar
over the years
oh,
I made share
for instance
of CBT
the NIV
Translation
team.
What an honor.
I just missed
the meeting
and got appointed
as a chair
which means
I have to do
all the
sacred stuff
for you.
I have to do
all the organizing.
You know,
oh,
what a privilege
you know,
you can put that
on your resume
there,
CBT,
you know,
and what actually
comes down to
the meaning
is that
there's a guy
who gets stuck
doing all
the behind-the-scenes
work
is what it means.
Privilege,
okay,
maybe to some degree
a lot of responsibility.
So,
the privilege
that we enjoy
given this new
access to God
and all the things
associated with it
brings the responsibility
to act
on that privilege.
So,
not unnaturally,
verse 22,
the first point
of application,
let us draw
near to God.
We have the
confidence to every,
we have the ability
to every,
because of Christ's
work in us.
So,
do it,
our authors say.
Draw near to God.
Draw near in worship
as we've been doing
already this morning.
Draw near in prayer
as we've been doing
this morning.
All kinds of ways
we can draw near
to God
to access
His presence
through our
high priest,
Jesus.
And we do that,
our author says,
with a sincere heart.
With the fullest
assurance
that faith
brings.
And faith
brings assurance.
Having our hearts
sprinkled
to cleanse us
from a guilty
conscience,
having our bodies
warped with
pure water.
Here again,
we are back
these imaginations
in the world
of the Jewish
sanctuary
and associated
sacrifices.
The high priest,
in order to enter
into that
Holy of Holies
once a year,
had to
slay animals
and had to
use their
blood
in order
to enter.
He had to
have his heart
sprinkled,
in a sense.
He had to
have his body
lost.
And I don't
think the
reference is
to baptism here.
Some people
think it is.
Possible.
But I think
it's just
again,
the Old
Testament
imagery
of sacrifice.
Look at
for instance,
chapter 9,
verse 19,
where our author
is talking about
the Old
Pregnant
rituals.
He took
the blood
of cows
together with
water,
scarlet wool
and branches
of his
and sprinkled
the scroll
on all the
people.
You see,
blood,
water,
sprinkling,
that's just
what our author
is saying
here in verse
22,
isn't it?
We have
experienced
that.
We have
been
praised
in this
way.
We have
been
enabled
to enter
into
the presence
of God.
So our author
is saying,
very simply,
do it.
answer,
draw near him.
Second,
that's
the backward
look that
it says.
In other
words,
think about
the Israelites
again.
One of those
Israelites
out there
in the wilderness
in a pilgrimage
from Egypt
to Thomas
Land.
And one of
the things
that again
and again
Scripture
encourages us
to do,
and now
encourages us
to do
as a new
covenant
people,
God,
look back
at what
God has
done.
Israel
encouraged
to go
and again.
Remember
what God
did for
you.
Remember
the
plagues
that God
brought
upon
Egypt
in order
to set
the people
free.
Remember
the Red
Sea.
Remember
the Passover.
the man
in the wilderness.
Remember
all those
unbelievable
things God
has done.
We're just
saying about
remembering
the goodness
of God.
This is what
the author
is telling us.
Like those
Israelites,
looking back
and what
God
has done
as assurance
for our
presence,
so our
author.
Verse 22
brings us
to look
down at
the time
when our
hearts were
sprinkled
and we
came to
know Jesus
as our
Savior and
his sacrificial
work was
applied to
our hearts
and
consciences.
Look
back,
but also
look forward.
And that is
one of the
really important
things about
the Christian
lives is that
we balance
those two
of us.
That we're
people who
are looking
back,
but also
who are
looking forward.
That we are
people who
are not only
looking back
and saying,
oh,
weren't those
great things
back there
when God
did these
things?
And we
just sort
of wallow
in the past.
We need
to look back,
yes,
but we need
to remember
that there
is a forward
look as well.
The Israelites
were on their
way somewhere.
They weren't
supposed to
just stay
out there
in the
desert,
were they?
No,
they were
on their
way to
a promised
land,
a land
flowing with
milk and
honey,
the Scripture
reminded us.
Yes,
a land
where there
were powerful
people already
as gods,
powerful people
who might
resist the
Israelites,
but nevertheless,
a land
God was
promising to
people.
So,
our author
tells us
then to
hold
unswervingly
to the
hope we
profess.
God has
something for
us,
not an
actual
territory,
a promised
land,
but he
has for
us an
eternal
place of
blessing
that he
is wanting
to lead
us toward
in our
Christian
pilgrimage.
We are
on our
way somewhere.
We are
not to be
stagnant.
We are
not just
to be
sitting out
in the
desert,
wondering
what God
is doing,
bewailing
maybe the
difficult
things that
have come
into our
lives,
years of
life are
being
tested,
the
readers of
Hebrews were
being tested
in persecution.
Many of
you are
going through
testing of
various kinds
as the world
throws up all
kinds of
testing and
trials in
our ways.
We are all
too keenly
aware.
But we are
supposed to
look beyond
those to
the promise
of what
God has
for us
ultimately
told unswervingly
to God
told.
For he
who promised
is faithful.
God is
faithful.
And this
brings up
what our
author has
said at
the end
of chapter
6,
if you
want to
look back
there,
we maybe
have time
now,
where he
brings
Abraham
into the
picture.
As a
paradigm of
that kind
of forward
look,
God promising
Abraham by
faith and
endurance,
accepting and
responding to
the promise
and receiving
the blessing
of the
fulfillment
of those
promises,
just as we
now have
the option
to experience
that fulfillment
as well.
The backward
look,
the forward
look.
Third,
the focus
on the
present,
verses 24
and 25.
As we
look back
and forward
and kind
of switch
gears maybe
from one
to the
other,
we are
to be
people
who are
loving
each other.
That's the
kind of
people we
are to
be in
the meantime.
That is
fundamental to
what it means
for us to
be Christians.
So the
else goes,
let us
consider how
we may
spur one
another on
toward love
and good
deeds.
Not giving
up meeting
together as
someone in
the habit
of doing,
but encouraging
one another
and all
the more
as you
see the
day
approaching.
the love
that we
display
toward one
another here
interestingly
has what
we might
call a
negative
side
and a
positive
side.
Our answer
begins with
the negative.
Let us
consider how
spur one
another
on.
Now,
I don't
agree with
everything in
the NAD.
If you
don't like
something in
the NAD,
that's a
vote I
lost on
the committee,
be assured.
But I do
like our
translation here
with the
word spur
because it
kind of
might remind
us a
little bit
of spur
ing on a
horse.
Digging one
spurs
under the
side of
that horse
to keep
it in
motion or
to get
it to
speed up.
It
reminds the
notion of
a little
bit of
an irritating
activity.
I mean,
it's exactly
what the
Greek word
is doing
here.
We are
to
irritate
each other.
So,
some of you,
that's the one
point you'll
take from
sermon.
Preachers are
doing these
heart blows
to irritate
folks.
You know,
I'm really
good at that
and I'm
just going
to use
that spiritual
gift and
be
irritating
everybody
around me.
No,
the point
is though,
we are
to have
a kind
of brotherly
and sisterly
love for
each other
that leads
us to get
involved in
people's
lives even
when they
don't like
it.
Sometimes
people need
to be
irritated.
Sometimes
they need
to be
confronted.
Sometimes
they need
to be
reminded
that maybe
they have
chosen a
path that
is contrary
to God's
word and
it's going
to lead
to problems
and difficulties
for them.
We need
to have
enough love
for one
another to
do that.
Tough love,
I guess we
could say.
Second,
there is a
positive side
of it.
Our author
says we're
also supposed
to be
encouraging
each other.
The author
reminds us
along the
way here
by the
way,
not giving
up meeting
together.
Having just
come through
the pandemic,
I think we've
learned some
lessons.
I think at
least in
our church,
which went
entirely online
for a number
of months
in order to
prevent the
spread of
COVID,
we accessed
our services
via YouTube,
as so many
people did
during those
days.
And we
only realized
how much
we missed
getting together
when we
started getting
together again.
And the
encouragement
of that
brought to
be sitting
around tables
with like-minded
people trying
to live the
same kind of
life we were,
learning from
their trials
and their
problems,
learning what
it means to
walk faithfully
before God
and their
father.
Those kinds
of things
happen when
we are
together
physically.
New Testament,
we could talk
about this for a
long time,
but I think
Scripture has a
very strong
emphasis on the
importance of
our bodies and
our bodily
connections with
each other.
It can't take
place if you're
sitting and
watching church
in your
pajamas with
a mug of
coffee.
It doesn't
happen.
It only
happens as
we come
together.
So that
was called
membership.
That's one
way we
identify with
people of
God in
this kind
of way.
We indicate
we're serious
about being
part of a
family,
brothers and
sisters,
who sometimes
are going to
be in our
face when
we need
it.
And other
times are
going to be
saying,
hey,
God is
faithful.
You're going
through a tough
time.
We're
surrounding you.
We're praying
for you.
We're doing
what we
found
specifically
to help
you out
in the
difficult
circumstances
you're in.
Great if
you have
fathers in
your families.
So many
families don't
have
families.
So many
families in
our life,
in our world,
are dysfunctional.
People are
looking for
a family.
This is a
place they
can find it.
We need to
encourage that.
work at being
the kind of
body of Christ
where these
things can
happen.
We can't do
life unless
we're
regularly
meeting
together.
As we
look back
at the
passages,
we've
probably seen
something that
is fairly
obvious.
Verse 22,
we are to
draw near
what foolish
terms of
faith brings.
23,
we are to
hold unswervingly
to hope.
Verse 24,
we're to
consider how
to spur
away another
arm toward
love.
That sounds
familiar to you?
Faith,
hope,
and love.
And the
triad of
Christian
virtues that
are held up
for us in
many places
in the New
Testament
Scripture.
These three
things are
often referred
to,
sometimes
individually,
sometimes in
connection with
each other,
sometimes with
all three of
them that we
have in
here.
So as we
think back
about this
passage,
and again,
we think
about our
pilgrimage
from our
Exodus
experience
when we
were saved
from the
kingdom of
Christ.
When we
think about
the future
God has for
us,
His destiny
for us
in the
eternal
realm,
experiencing
glory in
our bodies
with Jesus
in the new
heaven and
new earth,
as we think
about that
future,
looking back
in our
past,
then focusing
on our
current
situation
where loving
one another
is a
critical thing
you need to
be doing
as a
people of
God
together,
together
walking on
this road
of pilgrimage.
Let me pray.
Father, I
thank you for
this body of
Christ, for
the joy that
my life and
I have in
experiencing
this group of
believers and
finding fellowship.
where she came
this morning
together, and I
pray that this
might be a
congregation that
indeed, as they
look back at
what God has
done, anticipate
eagerly what
God has yet to
do, find
themselves as a
family, as
brothers and
sisters, loving
each other well.
With Christ's
glory we pray.
Amen.